<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="https://naev.org/">
  <id>https://naev.org/</id>
  <title>Naev Blarg</title>
  <updated>2021-12-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <link rel="self" href="https://naev.org/feed/index.xml" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <author>
    <name>Naev DevTeam</name>
    <uri>https://naev.org</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2021-12-12:/blarg/2021-12-12_0.9.0-beta.3/</id>
    <title type="html">Naev 0.9.0-beta.3</title>
    <published>2021-12-12T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2021-12-12_0.9.0-beta.3/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As the bugs start to settle down, it is time for a third 0.9.0 beta release.
This release fixes the issues listed below.
As always, please report any issues on &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/issues"&gt;this tracker&lt;/a&gt;,
and feel free to join our Discord chat (&lt;a href="https://discord.com/invite/nd2M5BR"&gt;invite&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get the new version you can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Opt-in to the &lt;code&gt;beta&lt;/code&gt; channel via steam&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/tag/v0.9.0-beta.3"&gt;Download the new version from here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="Attacking traders in a Pirate Hyena." src="/imgs/blarg/2021/screen1.png" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Attacking traders in a Pirate Hyena.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changes-since-090-beta2"&gt;Changes since 0.9.0-beta.2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed warning about cargo rush deliveries when you don’t know the best route&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed another crash related to pilot removal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed wonky backgrounds during death cutscenes, for the sake of &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; players of course&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed crash when techs are first patched to planets through unidiff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed potential spurious warnings about incomplete translations, even when running in English&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed failure to resolve regional translations (like &lt;code&gt;pt_BT&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;pt_PT&lt;/code&gt;) from the locale&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed VN log text overlap issues&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed commodities not being added through unidiff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed safe lane rendering alpha being wrong&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed misbehaviours with Maikki, Nelly 2, Shark 3, Shipwreck, Travelling Merchant, Warlords Battle, and Particle Physics 2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed backgrounds accumulating when messing with options&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed issues with board scripts getting deferred with respect to boarding script&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed some instances of background text interfering with how foreground text was drawn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed some missions causing trouble when saved/reloaded (due to dynamic factions)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed minor Ship AI issues (rename at game start)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed autonav via the map during a landing sequence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed autonav giving away autofollowed pilots and unknown destination systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improved speed and accuracy of autonav stopping&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improved mission marker behavior (show planets more, always clean up at end of mission)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kicked Empire patrols out of the Arandon system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gave pirate ships dodgier outfits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proofread too many parts of the game to mention&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI should only try to jump to systems with their faction presence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wrap OSD titles as necessary&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t allow illegal characters in pilot name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be kinder to old video drivers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More meow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More music&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2021-12-01:/blarg/2021-12-01_0.9.0-beta.2/</id>
    <title type="html">Naev 0.9.0-beta.2</title>
    <published>2021-12-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2021-12-01_0.9.0-beta.2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing like a release announcement to lure the bugs into the open.
Our second 0.9.0 beta release fixes the ones listed below.
As always, please report any issues on &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/issues"&gt;this tracker&lt;/a&gt;,
and feel free to join our Discord chat (&lt;a href="https://discord.com/invite/nd2M5BR"&gt;invite&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get the new version you can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Opt-in to the &lt;code&gt;beta&lt;/code&gt; channel via steam&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/tag/v0.9.0-beta.2"&gt;Download the new version from here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="Attacking traders in a Pirate Hyena." src="/imgs/blarg/2021/screen1.png" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Attacking traders in a Pirate Hyena.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changes-since-090-beta1"&gt;Changes since 0.9.0-beta.1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prevented Naev from losing the player’s (pre-0.9.0-beta) licenses on first load&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed missing credits and translation coverage data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prevented players from getting stranded without access to fuel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mission script fixes for “Helping Nelly” and “The one with the Visit”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Outfit script fix for “Weapons Ionizer”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed issues impacting at least some Windows / Intel graphics combinations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hulls are more widely available&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improved some of the map outfits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do not render systems with unknown assets as restricted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added gamma correction to Options&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed reproducible crash when boarded pilots get removed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added counterfeit licenses to pirate worlds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove minor energy malus from sensor array and jump detector&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electron burst cannon is no longer widely available&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improved phrasing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2021-12-01:/blarg/2021-11-31_0.9.0-beta.1/</id>
    <title type="html">Naev 0.9.0-beta.1</title>
    <published>2021-12-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2021-11-31_0.9.0-beta.1/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a very productive year. With almost 8,500 commits from 0.8.2. For
reference, this is roughly one third of all the commits in the entire Naev
source code have been done this last year. As you can guess, with so many
changes altering fundamental things including most of the core gameplay
mechanics, there is a high chance that many things have been broken and things
lack polish. For this reason, like with the 0.8.x releases, we are going to do
several betas as we near the final 0.9.0 release, which we hope to be able to
get out this year. Of course, this will depend on how many bugs and issues are
found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you try it and find any issues, please report them at &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/issues"&gt;the issue
tracker&lt;/a&gt;. Discussion about the game can be
had on Discord (&lt;a href="https://discord.com/invite/nd2M5BR"&gt;discord invite&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get the new version you can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Opt-in to the &lt;code&gt;beta&lt;/code&gt; channel via steam&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/tag/v0.9.0-beta.1"&gt;Download the new version from here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="Attacking traders in a Pirate Hyena." src="/imgs/blarg/2021/screen1.png" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Attacking traders in a Pirate Hyena.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id="full-changelog"&gt;Full Changelog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New mechanics
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added new utility outfits with complex effects&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Changed ship classification, removing rare classes while adding Interceptor and Battleship classes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Illegal cargo and ship-to-ship detection&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pilots can now go into stealth mode&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Systems have “safe lanes” patrolled by the governing faction&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Electronic warfare parameters are simplified and visible&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added escorts for hire&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Some simple minigames have been added&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Scramblers and jammers have fixed chance to mess up missiles depending on their resistance&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Restricted systems where dominant faction will attack on sight&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Some bulk freighter-class ships added&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Systems can have different effects on all ships in them&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fake transponder replaces fake id&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visual improvements
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New fancy system rendering effects&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ships and rockets now have engine trails&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Beam visuals have been made more flexible and pretty&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Jumping visuals improved&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Redid the shake visuals and added a small damage visual&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Most special effects implemented as shaders&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Most small visuals redone to be more visible and clean&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Similar presences are now merged in map&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Overhauled all the backgrounds&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gameplay changes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pirates split into multiple clans and marauders&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added discovery messages as you explore the universe&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Overhauled NPC AI&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Overhaul and rebalance of most outfits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wanted ships no longer aggro defense forces (bounties)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bribed pilots don’t become hostile again unless attacked&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stress now decreases based on ship mass&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Merged the Independent and Civilian factions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Game now tracks meta-data like ships destroyed and time played&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Trade lane routes made explicit&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More common and useful derelict ships&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Missiles have lock-on reduced and in-flight calibration added&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tutorial redone with Ship AI that is also accessible from the info menu&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New ships including the Starbridge&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quality of Life
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Autonav supports landing and boarding&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Comm window reworked and you can bribe multiple pilots at once&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Possible to change or unequip ships with deployed fighters&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More fine-grained autonav reset control by setting enemy distance&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added autoequip functionality&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Able to filter equipable outfits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Minimal view mode for the map&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More visible map markers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More in-game tutorial-ish explanations for new mechanics as you encounter them&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You can now favourite your ships to help with sorting&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Redid boarding window to be more intuitive and easier to loot what you want&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Paste support for input stuff&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Translation completion status is shown in the options&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New locations
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added gambling resort “Minerva Station”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Revamped and improved some existing locations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Several new planets and systems&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;40 New missions
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Challenge adversaries in the Crimson Gauntlet&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Follow happenings on “Minerva Station”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Invade the frontier with the Dvaered&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ship enthusiast quiz&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Deliver fancy contraband all over the universe&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Raid trader convoys&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rescue derelict crew&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Small early game tutorial-ish campaign&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Neutral campaign to transform the universe&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Help the Za’lek do particle physics&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Meow&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New translation(s) in progress: Czech, French, Korean, Portuguese, and Japanese&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engine Changes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added an optimizer to improve automatic outfitting choices&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A ton of new ship stat attributes have been added&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for Lua-based hooks in Outfits for complex behaviours&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for post-processing shaders&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added rendering and update hooks in the Lua API&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added image format support beyond PNG (notably WebP)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for arbitrary ship display classes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Game data now handled by PhysicsFS, allowing for multiple sources and easier modding&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Meson is now the only build system, and development builds can integrate all assets/translations without being installed&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fonts now use distance fields and much better in many cases&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improved how Lua was being loaded&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added library that supports lots of Love2D API in Naev&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added Visual Novel library&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added card games&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added dynamic factions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added dynamic commodities&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lua support for advanced sound effects&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Most markers and indicators use signed distance functions now&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Internally using linear colourspace&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Faction presence computed with base and bonus values&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Virtual assets have been redone and are more flexible than before&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Point value system for ships to help with presence and other things&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for shipstats at a system level&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Initial support for 3D models&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Proper support for line breaks in most languages&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Most objects (ships, planets, etc.) have tags that can be used from Lua&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lots of optimization&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2021-08-22:/blarg/2021-08-22_sporadic_naev_newsletter_vol_2/</id>
    <title type="html">Sporadic Naev Newsletter Vol. 2</title>
    <published>2021-08-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-08-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2021-08-22_sporadic_naev_newsletter_vol_2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So it’s been over 10 years from the first edition of our &lt;a href="/blarg/2010-07-16_sporadic_naev_newsletter_vol_1/"&gt;sporadic naev
newsletter&lt;/a&gt;,
so it seems like it might be a good time to have the second edition. In the
previous edition, we talked about the state of 0.5.0 and the introduction of
big systems and electronic warfare. In this edition, we’ll talk about the state
of 0.9.0 and new features like stealth and safe lanes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="state-of-090"&gt;State of 0.9.0&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve passed 5,500 commits from 0.8.2. This is going to be the largest amount of
content and changes from any release ever with tons of graphical improvements,
new mechanics, and new content added all over. It is already all live in the
nightly images which are available from both
&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/tag/nightly"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; and steam via the
opt-in beta. That said, it is recommended for you to back up your save or use a
new one if you attempt to do this. At the current moment, you will lose many
outfits and experience hiccups trying to use an old save game. Unlike the
official releases, the nightly is still rather unpolished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently there is no hard ETA for the release, but we hope to release it
within the year and follow a more timely release cycle. We hope that we’ll be
able to do a feature freeze in a couple of months and focus exclusively on
polish until the release. As always, we will release one or more betas before
the official release to try to debug potential issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="electronic-warfare-overhaul"&gt;Electronic Warfare Overhaul&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electronic warfare was originally introduced in 0.5.0. With the move to big
systems, it no longer made sense for all ships to be visible at all times.
Furthermore, we wanted to differentiate the roles between smaller and larger
ships, while aiding survivability of small ships by making it harder for the
largest of turrets to track them and hit them. While this worked well to some
extent, it was never transparent to the player. We’ve revamped it this time
around to be fully visible to the player. Each ship, depending on its mass and
bonuses, will have three separate values: detection, evasion, and stealth, that
control when the ship is first detected, when the ship details are shown and
scanning is possible, and finally how well the ship can stealth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="Electronic Warfare Redux - this time with understandable values!" src="/imgs/blarg/2021/SNN2/ewredux.png" width="500" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Electronic Warfare Redux - this time with understandable values!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hiding is the most important attribute that controls when ships are detected at
and affects both evasion and stealth. Evasion is usually 75% of detected at
value, and controls how well turrets and missiles track a ship. Furthermore, it
controls the distance at which a ship is scanned at. Scanning a ship allows you
to see the details of cargo and outfits. Furthermore, patrol ships will scan
your ship and make sure you don’t have illegal cargo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="Player being scanned by a fleet led by an Empire Admonisher." src="/imgs/blarg/2021/SNN2/scanning.png" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Player being scanned by a fleet led by an Empire Admonisher.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That leads us to the final mechanic: stealth! Stealth allows ships to become
completely invisible if no ships are within their stealth distance. When
stealthed, ships get a -50% penalty to all movement: max speed, thrust, and
turning. However, they cease to appear on all system sensors. This allows ships
to sneak past systems or ships, opening lots of opportunities for contraband,
piracy, and survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="Looking at nearby ships in stealth mode." src="/imgs/blarg/2021/SNN2/stealth.png" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Looking at nearby ships in stealth mode.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id="safe-lanes"&gt;Safe lanes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the last major gameplay changing features is safe lanes, which have been
recently incorporated into the main branch. Safe lanes consist of routes in
space that are more regularly patrolled. Most traders and factional systems
will use these routes, while areas away from space lanes will naturally lead to
more pirate activities. Core systems with many planets and stations will
naturally lead to more safe lanes, while systems far away from core systems
will end up having sparser lanes, or none at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="Safe lanes that look like Pacman." src="/imgs/blarg/2021/SNN2/safelanes.png" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Safe lanes that look like Pacman.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id="ship-classification-redux"&gt;Ship Classification Redux&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a more minor change, but rare ship classes, such as cruiser ships, or
motherships have been removed. Other similar classes have been merged, such as
heavy drones and fighters, which retain the name of fighters. Furthermore,
fighters have been split into fighters and interceptors (light fighters), and
cruisers have been split into cruisers and battleships (heavy cruisers). This
changes are mainly there for the equipment algorithm and AI to exploit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="rebalance"&gt;Rebalance&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly all the outfits in the game have been modified or completely revamped.
Core outfits and weapons have been designed to be based around 6 tiers:
interceptor, fighter, corvette, destroyer, cruiser, and battleship. Utility
outfits have been made to be based on conditional behaviour such as being below
a certain armour threshold, or temporary behaviours. Finally, structural
outfits have been made be stronger and play a more significant role in
outfitting and not being left as an afterthought. Many new outfits have been
added to fill in missing slots and roles, with many left to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="visual-novel-framework"&gt;Visual Novel Framework&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another fairly large change is a Lua based visual novel framework that has been
written from scratch. It allows to show images and special effects while having
text progressively appear. This greatly enhances some of the storytelling
ability of the game and allows creating more complex conditional branching
behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="A friendly Minerva Station Terminal informing the player about their tokens." src="/imgs/blarg/2021/SNN2/vn1.png" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;A friendly Minerva Station Terminal informing the player about their tokens.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the entire system is based on the &lt;a href="https://love2d.org/"&gt;LÖVE
framework&lt;/a&gt; which we recently started to partially support
by mimicking the API in Naev, and allows for nearly infinite customizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="The Visual Novel Framework has infinite flexibility." src="/imgs/blarg/2021/SNN2/vn2.png" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;The Visual Novel Framework has infinite flexibility.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id="future-steps"&gt;Future Steps&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of other improvements we have not mentioned in this newsletter:
linear programming-based equipment optimization, discoveries, new missions, new
ship attributes, more shader support, etc. We might go deeper into new features
in future blarg posts as we refine and polish the mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With regard to what is coming up, there are no too major things left to do.
Besides overall polish, which will take most of the time, some new missions
have to be written, in-system objects implemented, jamming rework, pricing
rebalance, and a few odd ends here and there. We’re hoping for a release within
this year, but given the ambition and scope of 0.9.0, we’d rather delay and
have a better release, than rush it and have it be unplayable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you wish to contribute to Naev, we have lots of things that can be done,
even without programming experience! From &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/issues/1835"&gt;making cooler beauty shops for comm
and shipyard window&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/issues/1866"&gt;adding an
uninhabited frontier&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/issues/1814"&gt;more loading
screens&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/wiki/Needed-Artwork%3A-Characters"&gt;new character
artwork&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/wiki/Needed-Artwork%3A-Outfits"&gt;new
outfit artwork&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/wiki/Mission-Scripting"&gt;more missions&lt;/a&gt;, gameplay
testing, etc.  Tasks to be done can be found on the &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/issues"&gt;issue
tracker&lt;/a&gt;, and discussion can be had on
&lt;a href="https://discord.com/invite/nd2M5BR"&gt;Discord&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concludes the Sporadic Naev Newsletter Vol. 2, and hopefully the next will
be sooner than 10 years from now.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2021-07-18:/blarg/2021-07-18_future_goes_boom/</id>
    <title type="html">Future Goes Boom</title>
    <published>2021-07-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-07-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2021-07-18_future_goes_boom/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is about development on Naev 0.9.0.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though explosions in space games generally defy the laws of physics, they
are some of the better and necessary eye-candy. However, explosions in Naev
remained unchanged since about 13 years ago. While not necessarily awful, they
have always left a bit more to be desired. One idea that has been around for
ages has been to try to redo them in procedural shaders to look better and more
variable. With the
&lt;a href="/blarg/2021-04-09_trails/"&gt;recent&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="/blarg/2021-05-02_jumping/"&gt;shader&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="/blarg/2021-07-02_beam_me_up/"&gt;improvements&lt;/a&gt;, it has
never been a better time to revamp the other special effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive video720p"&gt;
 &lt;div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 figure-img"&gt;
  &lt;video controls="" class="embed-responsive-item"&gt;
   &lt;source src="/videos/blarg/boom/asteroids.webm" type="video/webm;codecs=&amp;quot;vp9, opus&amp;quot;" /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Mace rocket mining is the best way to mine.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The explosions have been redone with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Volume_ray_casting"&gt;ray
marching&lt;/a&gt; and are completely
procedural: each explosion should be completely unique. Furthermore, the
explosion parameters can be tweaked to create plasma clouds or other special
effects, replacing a large amount of image-based animations we were using.
Images speak louder than words, so see for yourself the new explosions in
action!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive video720p"&gt;
 &lt;div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 figure-img"&gt;
  &lt;video controls="" class="embed-responsive-item"&gt;
   &lt;source src="/videos/blarg/boom/goddard.webm" type="video/webm;codecs=&amp;quot;vp9, opus&amp;quot;" /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Goddard-class cruisers bites the dust.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
</feed>

