<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="https://naev.org/">
  <id>https://naev.org/</id>
  <title>Naev Blarg</title>
  <updated>2023-12-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <link rel="self" href="https://naev.org/feed/index.xml" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <author>
    <name>Naev DevTeam</name>
    <uri>https://naev.org</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2023-12-09:/blarg/2023-12-09_0.11.0-beta.2/</id>
    <title type="html">Naev 0.11.0-beta.2</title>
    <published>2023-12-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-12-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2023-12-09_0.11.0-beta.2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During playtesting 0.11.0-beta.1, we’ve found a bunch of bugs and issues that
we’ve addressed. In particular, some of the more important ones include having
the slim GUI show what outfits are being activated, which is particularly
useful for toggle weapon sets, and fixed some issues with collisions making it
hard for fast weapons to hit their targets.
As always, please report any issues on &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/issues"&gt;this tracker&lt;/a&gt;,
and feel free to join our Discord or Matrix chatrooms. Find out more about them &lt;a href="https://naev.org/contact/"&gt;here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get the new version from any of the sources below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/v0.11.0-beta.2"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/github.svg" alt="Get - Github" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/598530/Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/steam.svg" alt="Get - Steam" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://naev.itch.io/naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/itchio.svg" alt="Get - Itch.io" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://flathub.org/apps/details/org.naev.Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/flathub.svg" alt="Get - Flathub" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="The player in a Sirius Preacher using the Seeking Chakra ability." src="/imgs/screenshots_0.11.0/seeking_chakra.webp" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;The player in a Sirius Preacher using the Seeking Chakra ability.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changes-since-0110-beta1"&gt;Changes since 0.11.0-beta.1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slim GUI now shows activated outfits and all weapons all the time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collision system reworked (again) to take into account fast moving particles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed collision polygons not properly being used&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added short names to some outfits such that they are easier to distinguish in the GUI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allied factions won’t help out the player against neutral targets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added missing graphics for meditation chambers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t allow giving the player names that can’t be saved&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Updated love.filesystem to 0.11 spec renaming mkdir to createDirectory, enumerate to getDirectoryItems, and adding remove&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed toggle weapon sets not turning off with only bolt weapons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hardened physics engine a bit to overflow that happens in 49 days of straight game time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed trivial memory leak in vpool&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allow buying local maps where they are not sold&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buffed Hunting Combat AI to 15% bonus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Made Weakness Harmonizer AI not appear as an active outfit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Outfit Lua function onshoot has been renamed onshootany&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can toggle point defense weapons on and off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI will turn off weapons ionizer when going for a kill&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Player’s new ships should start will all the default outfits, which fixes the some Sirius psychic tests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pilot.weapsetAdd follows the same logic as the normal equipping functions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;slim GUI uses primary/secondary colours like the info menu&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI should be less prone to jump before their leader&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed cargo being lost when swapping ships in missions and events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;chapter1&lt;/code&gt;: event claims all the systems just in case&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;poi&lt;/code&gt;: renamed ‘Pristine Derelict’ to ‘Unusual Derelict’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;poi_intro&lt;/code&gt;: fixed typo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;achack03&lt;/code&gt;: fixed mission not being acceptable and harja spawning forever&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;achack04&lt;/code&gt;: fixed missing formatting string&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;dv_bikers&lt;/code&gt;: made missiles significantly more dodgeable and changed location&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Translation updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2023-12-03:/blarg/2023-12-03_0.11.0-beta.1/</id>
    <title type="html">Naev 0.11.0-beta.1</title>
    <published>2023-12-03T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-12-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2023-12-03_0.11.0-beta.1/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s nearing the end of the year and that means time for a new Naev release!
This release is once again one that revamps a lot of existing features and
legacy code, while adding lots of new content and features. Like always,
instead of doing a release directly, we’re going to be doing a series of betas
to try to ensure as few bugs as possible sneak into the final release. We plan
to do the official release in about two weeks from now, but it will depend on
how many issues and the likes are found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this release changes a lot of how the game currently plays, and, while it
is highly recommended to start a new game, it should be possible to just load
up your old saves without too much stuff being changed. In particular, some of
the major changes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Significantly reworked universe map to fit existing lore&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;House Sirius completely reworked&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Significantly improved autonav that uses lanes and is configurable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reworked structural outfits and number of ship slots&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weapon sets are more simple with no distinction between weapons and non-weapons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Possible to legally obtain all “standard” factional ships and outfits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you try it and find any issues, please report them at &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/issues"&gt;the issue
tracker&lt;/a&gt;. Discussion about the game can be
had on one of the various discussion forums and chatrooms we have. Check them
out &lt;a href="https://naev.org/contact/"&gt;here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get the new version from any of the sources below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/v0.11.0-beta.1"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/github.svg" alt="Get - Github" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/598530/Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/steam.svg" alt="Get - Steam" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://naev.itch.io/naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/itchio.svg" alt="Get - Itch.io" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://flathub.org/apps/details/org.naev.Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/flathub.svg" alt="Get - Flathub" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="The player in a Sirius Preacher using the Seeking Chakra ability." src="/imgs/screenshots_0.11.0/seeking_chakra.webp" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;The player in a Sirius Preacher using the Seeking Chakra ability.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id="full-changelog"&gt;Full Changelog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gameplay Changes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Universe significantly overworked to be more consistent with lore
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;More landable uninhabited spobs, unique locations, and things to discover&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Reviewed and corrected many descriptions and placement of spobs and systems&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;More in-depth and fleshed out tag system for locations&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ship slots and mass limits reworked such that smaller ships get more utility/structural slots to work with&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Point defense systems that can shoot down missiles and torpedoes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Space object (planets, stations, etc.) properties affect quantity of missions available&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Moved many missions and events to the vn system&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can sometimes find POI events with a pulse scanner equipped when entering systems&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Changed the visuals for some of the nebulas (PSO, Mizar)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pirate bribes cost more depending on your fleet and are based on points not mass&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Missions are introduced less all at once to the player&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Blink drives are more flexible but use energy and generate heat&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Razor class weapons have been completely reworked&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can steal more than one outfit from a ship with high boarding bonus&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;diy-nerds: improved reward&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quality of Life
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Significantly improved autonav
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Configurable and can use lanes&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;More efficient at reaching target locations&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;New option like follow pilots through jumps or brake when going to positions&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Make it explicit when all the escorts have jumped or landed&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Escorts will keep their same loadout until the game restarts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Player ship is no longer translucent when in stealth as it is redundant with the stealth icon&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Show enemy/ally factions in the faction standing info window&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Space dust is properly anti-aliased&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Minor speed ups to patrol lane computations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try to enforce minimum number of articles in the news&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Independent patrol and bounty missions can be completed on more planets and stations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can hide or prioritize missions from the info menu&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Manual aiming model aims at the mouse location when the mouse is visible&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Travelling merchant tells you when new wares are available and should be easier to find&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lua Love API should be better at handling input and not apply keys held before started&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Increase time compression when disabled&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Inverted how hide, evasion, and stealth value percent bonuses work. Now lower is better&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hide locked slots without outfits as the player can’t do anything with them&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added volley mode to weapon sets that makes weapons fire as fast as possible, instead of staggered&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Autonav options are now player-specific and accessible via the info menu settings button&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Travelling merchant gives full details of the intrinsic outfits they provide&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Selected slots in the equipment window will only show outfits that fit&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Autonav routes consider distance travelled in-system&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Made stress more visible in the slim GUI&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reworked how stats are displayed to be more visible and intuitive&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can show all known outfits or ships in with the map find functionality&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Weapon sets much more flexible, verbose, and easy to use&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Weapon sets remember slots, not outfits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Route is visible on all map modes now&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Blink and flicker drives can use double tap arrow keys to move around&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Toolkit is cached in a framebuffer for much faster rendering&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Intrinsic outfit details now visible from the equipment menu&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Visually indicate which pilots are scanning the player on the overlay and radars&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can sell all outfits on any spob with an outfitter&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Enemies in patrol missions should not run away&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Changed the faction standing caps to allow the player to get all ships when maxed out. Will be decreased in the future as missions are added&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Slot icons to make it more clear what special slots a ship has&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;System markers and autonav TARGET marker will try to not overlap with jumps and spob names&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New Content
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New mechanic for House Sirius called flow to unlock psychic powers
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Gives passive bonuses to Sirius ships&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Outfits allow use on non-Sirius ships&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;8 new missions
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Finish the Minerva campaign&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Nebula refugees&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Many new events
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Abandoned stations with secrets&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Greedy pirates looking for domination&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Challenges of the mind&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Mysterious signals&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;More points of interest&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Many, many new systems and space objects
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;67 new star systems with 123 new space objects&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;New graphics for space objects&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tons of new outfits
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Sirius flow outfits&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Completely reworked Sirius weapons too&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Point defense systems&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;New accessories&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Intrinsic outfits&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;and more!&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Many new outfit graphics&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New NPC graphics&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More NPC and news messages&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added the Space Trader Society faction&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Custom death animations for many ships&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More ways to increase fleet capacity&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The pirate clans are now more differentiated in terms of AI behaviour and taunts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More factional landing messages&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rehabilitation missions have been made more factional and a new rehabilitation mission for the FLF is now available&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engine
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Map system viewer is more compact&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added hook.hail_spob&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Events support tags&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Editor supports tags&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Library to handle conditionals for mission computer missions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added support for disabling specific patrol lanes from being generated&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for Lua scripting for ships&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Changed api of evt.claim and misn.claim&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Missions/events load Lua as chunks instead of compiling each time&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Significant speed-ups in collision detection with quadtrees&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hooks “outfit_buy”, “outfit_sell”, “ship_sell”, and “ship_swap” pass Lua objects instead of strings&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ships can have extra descriptions that show up on mouse over&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More Lua API added such as pilot.armour, pilot.shield, or naev.missionList&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Soromid NPCs can have custom descriptions based on genetics&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improved VN API with vn.move, vn.musicVolume, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improved VN handling of non-ascii fonts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for generating munitions from outfits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improved derelict script to handle custom derelicts better&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Removed some custom environment and string handling functions for standard SDL ones (requires 2.0.18 now)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Better handling of user locales&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Weaker effects shouldn’t overwrite stronger ones anymore&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Spobs can use communication graphics&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Require OpenGL 3.2 for geometry shaders now&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for advanced collisions such as weapon on weapon, allowing for point defense weapons&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Renamed thrust to accel for more consistency and simplifications&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for buying intrinsic outfits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ship distress moved to the message framework&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Outfits have support for double tapping accel/left/right triggers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Removed toolkit fading effects&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for rendering images as SDFs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Significant loading time speed-up with multithreading&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Main menu more responsive when changing windows&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Typo and wording fixes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed many corner case crashes in the editor&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed cargo missions not being generated in some parts of the universe&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Game no longer crashes when loading save with persisted Lua pointing to nonexistent systems/spobs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Minor improvements to many existing missions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed crash when events trigger other events on creation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed autonav sometimes having trouble landing with reverse thrusters&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Qex races should be much less laggy now&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed some outfits using the wrong store images&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed system viewer not being consistent with map&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Player’s escort damage is counted towards players damage&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Avoid having missions duplicates for cases where they can significantly stack such as patrol missions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fire rate and action speed should affect damage and disable of beam weapons&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed some outfits not having “Activated Outfit” in their description&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed ships offering 100 fuel refuels twice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed some ships having trouble equipping because of stacking engine reroutes and such&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improved AI’s scanning behaviour to be more robust to stealth pulsing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed POI generating in extremely volatile systems&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed tutorial running during cinematics&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed active outfits not showing “activated outfit” in their summary sometimes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;FLF no longer become true allies of the Dreamer Clan to not limit the players actions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Made audio system more robust to runnning out of source errors&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2023-09-05:/blarg/2023-09-05_sporadic_naev_newsletter_vol_3/</id>
    <title type="html">Sporadic Naev Newsletter Vol. 3</title>
    <published>2023-09-05T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-09-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2023-09-05_sporadic_naev_newsletter_vol_3/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Rather than waiting 10 years again from the previous edition of our &lt;a href="/blarg/2021-08-22_sporadic_naev_newsletter_vol_2/"&gt;sporadic
naev newsletter&lt;/a&gt;,
we’ve only let 2 years pass this time. In this edition, we’ll talk about some
improvements in 0.10.0 that may have gone under the radar, and the upcoming
0.11.0 release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="state-of-0110"&gt;State of 0.11.0&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/compare/0.10.x...main"&gt;a ton of commits and content since
0.10.0&lt;/a&gt;, things are
starting to shape up for 0.11.0. This release has focused greatly on reworking
and improving existing systems by bringing up to modern standards. In
particular, things such as how weapons are implemented, how ship stats are
dealt with, autonav internals, npc/news/derelict internals, reworking old
missions into the visual novel system, etc. have been mainly rewritten to
improve shortcomings. While this is not really visible in the end product
directly, it has enabled a lots of new features and improved the overall
robustness of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this release is much more than just elimination of technical debt, as
this release features a lot of new content in pretty much every area of the
game: more events, more missions, more lore, more outfits, and more locations.
The icing on the cake are new mechanics such as point defense systems, flow
mechanics, and trials. Overall this is shaping up to be quite a large release
and we are excited to share it with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="universe-revisited"&gt;Universe Revisited&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href="/blarg/2023-02-12_universe_revisited/"&gt;mentioned before on the
blarg&lt;/a&gt;, the
universe has been completely rework for 0.11.0. The universe should have a much
more natural feel that matches the lore, with the Sol Nebula being more
omnipresent as you travel around. This has required significant changes to many
systems and system objects, so that many places you knew will probably seem
familiar but quite different at the same time. It may take a while to get used
to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="Stumbling upon a ruined space station in the Nebula." src="/imgs/blarg/2023/nebula_ruined_station.png" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Stumbling upon a ruined space station in the Nebula.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In numbers, some 67 new systems and 123 new space objects have been added,
mainly around the Sol Nebula to give a more in-depth sensation of destruction
and the fragility of humankind. Besides the typical planets and stations, these
systems also contain many secrets that you can uncover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="house-sirius-rework"&gt;House Sirius Rework&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 0.10.0, the Soromid got a major rework by getting true bioships that can
level up and learn different skills, now it’s only fair for the neglected House
Sirius to also get the same treatment. Instead of extreme biological
engineering, House Sirius relies on psychic abilities called flow. While
individuals don’t possess very strong powers by themselves, House Sirius
has designed their ships to be powerful amplifiers to be able to unleash potent
abilities on the battle field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="The player unleashing an astral projection made of psychic energy to fight for them against pirates." src="/imgs/blarg/2023/sirius_astral_projection.png" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;The player unleashing an astral projection made of psychic energy to fight for them against pirates.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The player will also be able to obtain similar psychic powers and unlock the
full potential through new tests that can be found throughout space. Each
test will require the player to overcome obstacles in order to unlock new
abilities and also increase their overall psychic powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="Complete tests to unlock new psychic powers." src="/imgs/blarg/2023/sirius_test.png" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Complete tests to unlock new psychic powers.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Sirius ships have flow capability built-in, other ships can also use
structural outfits to enable flow capability, allowing for more customization.
That said, Sirius ships get unique bonuses from flow powers which are not
available to other ships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="plugin-system"&gt;Plugin System&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the &lt;a href="/blarg/2022-12-23_0.10.0/"&gt;plugin system was introduced in
0.10.0&lt;/a&gt;, it has gone largely
unnoticed. Currently, it is possible to replace and modify all parts of the
Naev that are implemented in Lua, which includes important parts such as
&lt;a href="/blarg/2023-07-30_new_autonav/"&gt;autonav&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="/blarg/2021-06-06_lua_outfits/"&gt;many
outfits&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="/blarg/2023-07-18_ships_go_boom/"&gt;ship
explosions&lt;/a&gt;, and more!
Not only that, Naev has option networking built in with
&lt;a href="http://enet.bespin.org/"&gt;enet&lt;/a&gt;, allowing for networking functionality. On this
line, there is a very much WIP &lt;a href="https://github.com/ThrosturX/naev-multiplayer"&gt;multiplayer
plugin&lt;/a&gt;, that allows for playing
with other people. To make development somewhat easier, a &lt;a href="https://naev.org/devmanual/"&gt;development
manual&lt;/a&gt; is being worked on, which covers things
like how to write content for Naev and how to structure plugins. Given the
advanced programming possibilities with the &lt;a href="https://naev.org/api/"&gt;Naev Lua
API&lt;/a&gt;, the only limit is your imagination!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="The simple shader plugin can be useful for older hardware." src="/imgs/blarg/2023/plugins_menu.png" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;The simple shader plugin can be useful for older hardware.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, there is &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/total_conversion_plugin_example"&gt;explicit support for total
conversions&lt;/a&gt; too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="new-content"&gt;New Content&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also a bunch of new content being worked on. Not only have the NPCs and
news you can find at the spaceport bar been greatly reworked to me more
relevant to the context at hand, but many new missions, factions, and
mechanisms have been implemented. The new universe has also given opportunities
to diversify the different factions and make them feel more unique, from taunts
to landing messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, with optimizations done to the engine, it’s finally possible to
have efficient point defense systems, something that has been asked for by
players for a long time. Point defense systems will automatically target nearby
missiles, torpedoes, and even interceptors! Of course the exact specs will
depend on the outfit, Guardian Systems use powerful lasers to focus on
torpedoes or interceptors, while Soromid Spittle Clusters have been
bio-engineered to create screens of bubbles to block weaker, but faster
missiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="A Soromid Ira trying to stop incoming torpedoes with spittle." src="/imgs/blarg/2023/spittle.png" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;A Soromid Ira trying to stop incoming torpedoes with spittle.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new neutral faction has been created to replace the old Trader’s Guild. The
new Space Traders Society is an organization that spans different guilds and
has important subfactions such as the mercenary guild Astra Vigilis, the Mining
Vrata, and the Imperial Red Star. They have important presence in several
systems where new outfits are also available for trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="The Mining Vrata Guildhouse." src="/imgs/blarg/2023/mining_vrata.png" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;The Mining Vrata Guildhouse.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, more events missions have been added throughout the universe, and although
not finished yet, we expect the conclusion to the Minerva campaign to make it
into 0.11.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="game-optimization"&gt;Game Optimization&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One issue Naev has traditionally had with the large systems it features, is
slow downs when many pilots were fighting each other as a result of a primitive
collision system. Well, it is no longer an issue as the current system has been
reworked with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadtree"&gt;quadtrees&lt;/a&gt;. Testing
shows that it is much much faster in extreme cases, with the game easily
handling hundreds of ships fighting each other without slowing down.
Furthermore, many aspects of the game have been profiled and optimized such
that the game should run much more fluid than 0.10.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="Naev running smoothly at 60 FPS despite 50 Dvaered Vendettas fighting with 50 FLF Lancelots." src="/imgs/blarg/2023/skirmish_benchmark.png" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Naev running smoothly at 60 FPS despite 50 Dvaered Vendettas fighting with 50 FLF Lancelots.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tests show that where Naev 0.10.0 would choke and become a slide show, Naev
0.11.0 will be able to run without a hitch, such as 50 Dvaered Vendettas
fighting with 50 FLF Lancelots. That said, given the high levels of time
compressions capital ships can reach, it is likely in some extreme cases you
may experience some slow downs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="concluding-remarks"&gt;Concluding Remarks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concludes the Sporadic Naev Newsletter Vol. 3, and see you again in
the next one!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2023-07-30:/blarg/2023-07-30_new_autonav/</id>
    <title type="html">New Autonav</title>
    <published>2023-07-30T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2023-07-30_new_autonav/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is about development on Naev 0.11.0.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pirates have always been an issue for the law-abiding player. They are
everywhere and relentless. However, with the
&lt;a href="/blarg/2021-08-22_sporadic_naev_newsletter_vol_2/"&gt;addition of patrol lanes in 0.9.0&lt;/a&gt;,
the universe has become a safer place, at least where the patrol lanes exist.
Although that made things much easier for the player, a gaping flaw was that
the autonav system did not understand how to use these lanes. For 0.11.0, we
implemented the long awaited feature that &lt;strong&gt;autonav will now use patrol lanes
if configured to!&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive video720p"&gt;
 &lt;div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 figure-img"&gt;
  &lt;video controls="" class="embed-responsive-item"&gt;
   &lt;source src="/videos/blarg/2023_07_autonav_the_lanes.webm" type="video/webm;codecs=&amp;quot;vp9, opus&amp;quot;" /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;A Llama using the autonav system to stick to patrol lanes.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how does this work? By default, autonav will use patrol lanes of non-hostile
factions when jumping, and will not use them otherwise. You can configure it to
not use lanes for jump, and also to use lanes for landing on planets or
stations from the new settings option accessible in the info menu. The settings
button replaces and incorporates the “Set GUI” functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="New player settings are accessible from the info window." src="/imgs/blarg/2023/autonav_settings.png" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;New player settings are accessible from the info window.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get this working the entire autonav system was scrapped and rewritten, this
also has the added effect of being much more accurate and efficient when
travelling around. Overall it’s a win-win situation! Hopefully this will ease
the early game and save many pilots from meeting their fate at the hands of the
hordes of marauders lurking in the darkness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, you can opt-in to the &lt;code&gt;nightly&lt;/code&gt; beta branch on steam, or download
the nightly from itch.io or github to get the latest and greatest of Naev
development. Due note that this can be unstable, and make sure to back up your
0.10 saves first!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2023-07-18:/blarg/2023-07-18_ships_go_boom/</id>
    <title type="html">Ships Go Boom</title>
    <published>2023-07-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2023-07-18_ships_go_boom/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is about development on Naev 0.11.0.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the 2nd anniversary of posting about implementing &lt;a href="/blarg/2021-07-18_future_goes_boom/"&gt;raymarched fancy explosions&lt;/a&gt;,
it’s time to talk about trying to use the system to its full potential. And by
full potential, I mean custom ship explosions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the factional ships have been given custom explosions, some slightly
different from the “standard” explosions, while others have much more radical
changes, including different explosion types, secondary effects, and radically
different colours. Time to explode and damage have also been changed, while
some explosions now do different damage types and/or apply disabling effects.
This should help have the different factions and ships feel more different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive video720p"&gt;
 &lt;div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 figure-img"&gt;
  &lt;video controls="" class="embed-responsive-item"&gt;
   &lt;source src="/videos/blarg/2023_07_explosions.webm" type="video/webm;codecs=&amp;quot;vp9, opus&amp;quot;" /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Showcase of the different faction ship explosions.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the technical side of things, custom ship explosions are done by using Lua
scripting for ships, similar as what was &lt;a href="/blarg/2021-06-06_lua_outfits/"&gt;done for outfits&lt;/a&gt;. This opens up a whole new
possibility of what can be done with ships, I won’t cover other things being
done with this yet, but it has to do with the Great House Sirius rework which
brings about psychic powers. All these changes will be included in version
0.11.0 which should be released around December this year. Lots of exciting
development to look for for the rest of 2023!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
</feed>

