<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="https://naev.org/">
  <id>https://naev.org/</id>
  <title>Naev Blarg</title>
  <updated>2024-01-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <link rel="self" href="https://naev.org/feed/index.xml" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <author>
    <name>Naev DevTeam</name>
    <uri>https://naev.org</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2024-01-15:/blarg/2024-01-15_0.11.2/</id>
    <title type="html">Naev 0.11.2</title>
    <published>2024-01-15T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-01-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2024-01-15_0.11.2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Inside the improvements of 0.11.1, a critical bug that seems to affect
release-version windows only sneaked in. This bug causes autonav to basically
crash the game when activated in certain conditions. Given that this makes the
game pretty much unplayable on affected systems, we created a new version that
should solve the issue. Thanks to all those reported and involved in the
fixing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get the latest version from any of the following sources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/v0.11.2"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/github.svg" alt="Get - Github" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/598530/Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/steam.svg" alt="Get - Steam" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://naev.itch.io/naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/itchio.svg" alt="Get - Itch.io" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://flathub.org/apps/details/org.naev.Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/flathub.svg" alt="Get - Flathub" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive video720p"&gt;
 &lt;div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 figure-img"&gt;
  &lt;video controls="" class="embed-responsive-item"&gt;
   &lt;source src="/videos/0.11.0_trailer.webm" type="video/webm;codecs=&amp;quot;vp9, opus&amp;quot;" /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Naev 0.11.0 official trailer.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id="full-changelog"&gt;Full Changelog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stopped autonav from preventing wobble and overshooting by crashing the entire game&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2024-01-14:/blarg/2024-01-14_0.11.1/</id>
    <title type="html">Naev 0.11.1</title>
    <published>2024-01-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-01-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2024-01-14_0.11.1/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Naev DevTeam is proud to announce the release of Naev version 0.11.1. This
update fixes some issues on certain platforms with video memory corruption and
crashes, and a myriad of smaller issues here and there. It is highly
recommended to update to the newest version.  We would like to thank all the
contributors who have participated and helped in the making of this release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get the latest version from any of the following sources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/v0.11.1"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/github.svg" alt="Get - Github" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/598530/Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/steam.svg" alt="Get - Steam" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://naev.itch.io/naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/itchio.svg" alt="Get - Itch.io" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://flathub.org/apps/details/org.naev.Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/flathub.svg" alt="Get - Flathub" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive video720p"&gt;
 &lt;div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 figure-img"&gt;
  &lt;video controls="" class="embed-responsive-item"&gt;
   &lt;source src="/videos/0.11.0_trailer.webm" type="video/webm;codecs=&amp;quot;vp9, opus&amp;quot;" /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Naev 0.11.0 official trailer.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id="full-changelog"&gt;Full Changelog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Give all ammo back to player after doing obelisk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed player being invincible after completing an obelisk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed a crash when loading games while a landing hook was running&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed race condition in threadpool&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed asteroids spawning in not proper shapes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed autonav wobble and overshooting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Point defense won’t shoot at disabled pilots anymore&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed battery descriptions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discovering a hidden jump will make both directions known&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed AI trying to scan hostile targets they lost track of&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Properly save and load &lt;code&gt;reward_value&lt;/code&gt; to and from saves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed events and missions being able to trigger in obelisk tests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed beam weapons not hitting asteroids&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Properly compute weapon range with &lt;code&gt;launch_range&lt;/code&gt; modifiers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed some range checks with inrange weapon sets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed Empire Pacifier mass being too low&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed warning when looking at internal flow amplifier descriptions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Removed Soromid Ira turret and forward weapon stats&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed reality rip and avatar of sirichana abilities giving errors when the AI tries to use them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed issue on some systems with indexed images&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed pirates and pilots that don’t care being able to disable the fake transponder&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can now see and target allies that are stealthed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pheromone emitter won’t do anything in exclusively claimed systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed some weapons such as beams not hitting targets other than selected one&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed rendering order making it so most effects were below the player&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed fallback switch weapon sets not being found properly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed bioship “Wanderer” perk giving absolute accel bonus instead of relative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased Neural Accelerator Interface energy regen malus to -100%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;zalek/blackhole/zbh09&lt;/code&gt;: don’t error out when a bioship ceases to exist&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;kidnapped/traffic_00&lt;/code&gt;: fixed formatting string telling the player what system to go to&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;kidnapped/traffic_01&lt;/code&gt;: ship should spawn if taking off in the same system, not just jumping in&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;tutorial/nelly01&lt;/code&gt;: fixed derelict message not appearing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;minerva/pirate4&lt;/code&gt;: fixed save me spam only being print once&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;neutral/seek_n_destroy&lt;/code&gt;: fixed warnings when taking off in the same system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;sirius/achack/achack01&lt;/code&gt;: fixed not being able to accept mission&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;dvaered/dv_diversion&lt;/code&gt;: fixed not being able to accept mission&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;dvaered/dv_bikers&lt;/code&gt;: don’t allow the player to use escorts and properly update mission TODO&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;sirius/achack03&lt;/code&gt;: fixed not being able to complete the mission&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;neutral/kidnapped&lt;/code&gt;: fixed inconsistency in the name of the system to go to&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;shadow/shadowrun&lt;/code&gt;: fixed VN issues not allowing mission completion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;shadow/shadowrun&lt;/code&gt;: changed locations to make it possible to do in the allotted time-frame&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;shadow/shadowvigil&lt;/code&gt;: fixed Seiryuu not appearing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;shiplover&lt;/code&gt;: don’t ask the player about ships they can’t obtain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed many typos&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Translation updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2023-12-23:/blarg/2023-12-23_0.11.0/</id>
    <title type="html">Naev 0.11.0</title>
    <published>2023-12-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-12-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2023-12-23_0.11.0/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Following the winter tradition, the Naev DevTeam is proud to announce the
release of version 0.11.0.
This is again quite a large release that has rewritten and reworked large parts
of the engine and long-established mechanics to be more flexible, faster, and
efficient.
Many long-term players will notice that many things they had gotten used to
have been changed, starting from the Naev universe itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank all the contributors who have participated and helped in
the making of this release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most notable changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reworked universe map to fit existing lore&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;House Sirius completely reworked&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improved autonav that uses lanes and is configurable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reworked structural outfits and number of ship slots&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weapon sets are more simple with no distinction between weapons and non-weapons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Possible to legally obtain all “standard” factional ships and outfits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Point defense weapons that automatically fire at fighters and missiles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A lot more content&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Significant engine speed-ups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get the latest version from any of the following sources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/v0.11.0"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/github.svg" alt="Get - Github" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/598530/Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/steam.svg" alt="Get - Steam" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://naev.itch.io/naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/itchio.svg" alt="Get - Itch.io" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://flathub.org/apps/details/org.naev.Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/flathub.svg" alt="Get - Flathub" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new version should be compatible with older save games, and will update
things as necessary. However, in this release, given the big changes done to
the universe, old saves will potentially have the their universe map in a bit
of a mess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive video720p"&gt;
 &lt;div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 figure-img"&gt;
  &lt;video controls="" class="embed-responsive-item"&gt;
   &lt;source src="/videos/0.11.0_trailer.webm" type="video/webm;codecs=&amp;quot;vp9, opus&amp;quot;" /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Naev 0.11.0 official trailer.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id="full-changelog"&gt;Full Changelog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gameplay Changes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Universe significantly overworked to be more consistent with lore
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;More landable uninhabited spobs, unique locations, and things to discover&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Reviewed and corrected many descriptions and placement of spobs and systems&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;More in-depth and fleshed out tag system for locations&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ship slots and mass limits reworked such that smaller ships get more utility/structural slots to work with&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Point defense systems that can shoot down missiles and torpedoes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Space object (planets, stations, etc.) properties affect quantity of missions available&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Moved many missions and events to the vn system&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can sometimes find POI events with a pulse scanner equipped when entering systems&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Changed the visuals for some of the nebulas (PSO, Mizar)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pirate bribes cost more depending on your fleet and are based on points not mass&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Missions are introduced less all at once to the player&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Blink drives are more flexible but use energy and generate heat&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Razor class weapons have been completely reworked&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can steal more than one outfit from a ship with high boarding bonus&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Differentiated more significantly the energy / kinetic / plasma weapon types&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;diy-nerds: improved reward&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quality of Life
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Significantly improved autonav
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Configurable and can use lanes&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;More efficient at reaching target locations&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;New option like follow pilots through jumps or brake when going to positions&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Make it explicit when all the escorts have jumped or landed&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Escorts will keep their same loadout until the game restarts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Player ship is no longer translucent when in stealth as it is redundant with the stealth icon&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Show enemy/ally factions in the faction standing info window&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Space dust is properly anti-aliased&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Minor speed ups to patrol lane computations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try to enforce minimum number of articles in the news&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Independent patrol and bounty missions can be completed on more planets and stations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can hide or prioritize missions from the info menu&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Manual aiming model aims at the mouse location when the mouse is visible&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Travelling merchant tells you when new wares are available and should be easier to find&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lua Love API should be better at handling input and not apply keys held before started&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Increase time compression when disabled&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Inverted how hide, evasion, and stealth value percent bonuses work. Now lower is better&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hide locked slots without outfits as the player can’t do anything with them&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added volley mode to weapon sets that makes weapons fire as fast as possible, instead of staggered&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Autonav options are now player-specific and accessible via the info menu settings button&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Travelling merchant gives full details of the intrinsic outfits they provide&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Selected slots in the equipment window will only show outfits that fit&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Autonav routes consider distance travelled in-system&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Made stress more visible in the slim GUI&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reworked how stats are displayed to be more visible and intuitive&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can show all known outfits or ships in with the map find functionality&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Weapon sets much more flexible, verbose, and easy to use&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Weapon sets remember slots, not outfits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Route is visible on all map modes now&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Blink and flicker drives can use double tap arrow keys to move around&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Toolkit is cached in a framebuffer for much faster rendering&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Intrinsic outfit details now visible from the equipment menu&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Visually indicate which pilots are scanning the player on the overlay and radars&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can sell all outfits on any spob with an outfitter&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Enemies in patrol missions should not run away&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Changed the faction standing caps to allow the player to get all ships when maxed out. Will be decreased in the future as missions are added&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Slot icons to make it more clear what special slots a ship has&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;System markers and autonav TARGET marker will try to not overlap with jumps and spob names&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Slim GUI uses primary/secondary colours like the info menu&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Slim GUI now shows activated outfits and all weapons all the time&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added short names to some outfits such that they are easier to distinguish in the GUI&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New Content
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New mechanic for House Sirius called flow to unlock psychic powers
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Gives passive bonuses to Sirius ships&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Outfits allow use on non-Sirius ships&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;8 new missions
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Finish the Minerva campaign&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Nebula refugees&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;24 new events
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Abandoned stations with secrets&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Greedy pirates looking for domination&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Challenges of the mind&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Mysterious signals&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;More points of interest&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;67 new star systems with 123 new space objects
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;More interesting and unusal locations&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Many new unique graphics&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;37 new outfits
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Sirius flow outfits&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Completely reworked Sirius weapons too&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Point defense systems&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;New accessories&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Intrinsic outfits&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;and more!&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Many new outfit graphics&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New NPC graphics&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More NPC and news messages&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added the Space Trader Society faction&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Custom death animations for many ships&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More ways to increase fleet capacity&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The pirate clans are now more differentiated in terms of AI behaviour and taunts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More factional landing messages&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rehabilitation missions have been made more factional and a new rehabilitation mission for the FLF is now available&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engine
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Map system viewer is more compact&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added hook.hail_spob&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Events support tags&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Editor supports tags&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Library to handle conditionals for mission computer missions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added support for disabling specific patrol lanes from being generated&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for Lua scripting for ships&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Changed api of evt.claim and misn.claim&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Missions/events load Lua as chunks instead of compiling each time&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Significant speed-ups in collision detection with quadtrees&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hooks “outfit_buy”, “outfit_sell”, “ship_sell”, and “ship_swap” pass Lua objects instead of strings&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ships can have extra descriptions that show up on mouse over&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More Lua API added such as pilot.armour, pilot.shield, or naev.missionList&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Soromid NPCs can have custom descriptions based on genetics&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improved VN API with vn.move, vn.musicVolume, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improved VN handling of non-ascii fonts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for generating munitions from outfits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improved derelict script to handle custom derelicts better&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Removed some custom environment and string handling functions for standard SDL ones (requires 2.0.18 now)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Better handling of user locales&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Weaker effects shouldn’t overwrite stronger ones anymore&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Spobs can use communication graphics&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Require OpenGL 3.2 for geometry shaders now&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for advanced collisions such as weapon on weapon, allowing for point defense weapons&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Renamed thrust to accel for more consistency and simplifications&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for buying intrinsic outfits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ship distress moved to the message framework&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Outfits have support for double tapping accel/left/right triggers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Removed toolkit fading effects&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for rendering images as SDFs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Significant loading time speed-up with multithreading&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Main menu more responsive when changing windows&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Typo and wording fixes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed many corner case crashes in the editor&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed cargo missions not being generated in some parts of the universe&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Game no longer crashes when loading save with persisted Lua pointing to nonexistent systems/spobs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Minor improvements to many existing missions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed crash when events trigger other events on creation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed autonav sometimes having trouble landing with reverse thrusters&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Qex races should be much less laggy now&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed some outfits using the wrong store images&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed system viewer not being consistent with map&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Player’s escort damage is counted towards players damage&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Avoid having missions duplicates for cases where they can significantly stack such as patrol missions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fire rate and action speed should affect damage and disable of beam weapons&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed some outfits not having “Activated Outfit” in their description&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed ships offering 100 fuel refuels twice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed some ships having trouble equipping because of stacking engine reroutes and such&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improved AI’s scanning behaviour to be more robust to stealth pulsing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed POI generating in extremely volatile systems&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed tutorial running during cinematics&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed active outfits not showing “activated outfit” in their summary sometimes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;FLF no longer become true allies of the Dreamer Clan to not limit the players actions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Made audio system more robust to running out of source errors&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;AI should be less prone to jump before their leader&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;AI will turn off weapons ionizer when going for a kill&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hardened physics engine a bit to overflow that happens in 49 days of straight game time&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Don’t allow giving the player names that can’t be saved&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Allied factions won’t help out the player against neutral targets&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed pilot.setSpeedLimit not working&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Show tracking icons for non-turret bolt weapons too&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Have ships be a little less spammy distressing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Gave unicorp storm launchers a rarity of 2 and made it more available&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed resizing not working on the background and toolkit in some cases&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Turn off all weapon sets when entering stealth or changing type&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Map’s discovery mode shows system features&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed rare hard crash when beams are being fired&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed crash when change tab triggers a takeoff&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Buffed Scanning Combat AI to have an additional +15% tracking&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Buffed weapon ionizer to only -50% damage from -70% damage&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Soromid Arx now has one non-exclusive heavy non-bio slot&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can only start to afterburn with enough energy for 0.5 seconds of afterburning&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Consider beam width when computing collisions&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2023-12-14:/blarg/2023-12-14_0.11.0-beta.3/</id>
    <title type="html">Naev 0.11.0-beta.3</title>
    <published>2023-12-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-12-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2023-12-14_0.11.0-beta.3/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During playtesting 0.11.0-beta.2, we’ve found even more issues that have been
fixed, including some hard crashes and some inconsistencies with weapon set
behaviours. Additionally, lots more quality of life usability such as in range
weapon sets only shooting when enemies are in arcs have also been added. We’re
hoping this to be the last beta before the official release which should hit in
a week or so. As always, please report any issues on &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/issues"&gt;this
tracker&lt;/a&gt;, and feel free to join our
Discord or Matrix chatrooms. Find out more about them
&lt;a href="https://naev.org/contact/"&gt;here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get the new version from any of the sources below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/v0.11.0-beta.3"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/github.svg" alt="Get - Github" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/598530/Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/steam.svg" alt="Get - Steam" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://naev.itch.io/naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/itchio.svg" alt="Get - Itch.io" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://flathub.org/apps/details/org.naev.Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/flathub.svg" alt="Get - Flathub" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="The player in a Sirius Preacher using the Seeking Chakra ability." src="/imgs/screenshots_0.11.0/seeking_chakra.webp" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;The player in a Sirius Preacher using the Seeking Chakra ability.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changes-since-0110-beta2"&gt;Changes since 0.11.0-beta.2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Differentiated more significantly the energy / kinetic / plasma weapon types&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed hard crash when loading when approaching certain NPCs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed crash when change tab triggers a takeoff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed Naev not starting on Mac OS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed beam collisions (again)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed rare hard crash when beams are being fired&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘in range’ option for weapon sets now takes into account weapon arcs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buffed Targeting Conduit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Renamed ‘Point of Interest’ to ‘Sensor Anomaly’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Double-tap activating outfits breaks stealth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nerfed Sirius Fidelity so it can no longer get ludicrous levels of action speed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Map’s discovery mode shows system features&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Removed enemies from a certain hidden faction so the player won’t have standing issues with them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Non-weapon outfits no longer show switch groups they are in as hot keys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turn off weapon sets when changing type&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed toggle weapon sets not triggering outfits over and over as expected&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turn off all weapon sets when entering stealth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed resizing not working on the background and toolkit in some cases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added pilot.weapsetAddType and pilot.weapsetSetActive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gave unicorp storm launchers a rarity of 2 and made it more available&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have ships be a little less spammy distressing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Centered tracking icon in slim GUI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Show tracking icons for non-turret bolt weapons too&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More short names for weapon outfits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed pilot.setSpeedLimit not working&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added tutorial message when player acquires first point defense weapon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;test_of_renewal&lt;/code&gt;: fixed weapon set defaults being incorrect and increased enemy damage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;seek_n_destroy&lt;/code&gt;: missions should work properly when boarding the target&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;flf_diversion&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;flf_rogue&lt;/code&gt;: Missions should no longer be able to have ridiculously low credit rewards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;ec00&lt;/code&gt;: changed it so you can’t hail the collective drone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;escort&lt;/code&gt;: fixed pilots not flying in formation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed many typos&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Translation updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2023-12-09:/blarg/2023-12-09_0.11.0-beta.2/</id>
    <title type="html">Naev 0.11.0-beta.2</title>
    <published>2023-12-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-12-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2023-12-09_0.11.0-beta.2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During playtesting 0.11.0-beta.1, we’ve found a bunch of bugs and issues that
we’ve addressed. In particular, some of the more important ones include having
the slim GUI show what outfits are being activated, which is particularly
useful for toggle weapon sets, and fixed some issues with collisions making it
hard for fast weapons to hit their targets.
As always, please report any issues on &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/issues"&gt;this tracker&lt;/a&gt;,
and feel free to join our Discord or Matrix chatrooms. Find out more about them &lt;a href="https://naev.org/contact/"&gt;here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get the new version from any of the sources below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/v0.11.0-beta.2"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/github.svg" alt="Get - Github" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/598530/Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/steam.svg" alt="Get - Steam" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://naev.itch.io/naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/itchio.svg" alt="Get - Itch.io" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://flathub.org/apps/details/org.naev.Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/flathub.svg" alt="Get - Flathub" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="The player in a Sirius Preacher using the Seeking Chakra ability." src="/imgs/screenshots_0.11.0/seeking_chakra.webp" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;The player in a Sirius Preacher using the Seeking Chakra ability.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changes-since-0110-beta1"&gt;Changes since 0.11.0-beta.1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slim GUI now shows activated outfits and all weapons all the time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collision system reworked (again) to take into account fast moving particles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed collision polygons not properly being used&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added short names to some outfits such that they are easier to distinguish in the GUI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allied factions won’t help out the player against neutral targets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added missing graphics for meditation chambers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t allow giving the player names that can’t be saved&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Updated love.filesystem to 0.11 spec renaming mkdir to createDirectory, enumerate to getDirectoryItems, and adding remove&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed toggle weapon sets not turning off with only bolt weapons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hardened physics engine a bit to overflow that happens in 49 days of straight game time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed trivial memory leak in vpool&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allow buying local maps where they are not sold&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buffed Hunting Combat AI to 15% bonus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Made Weakness Harmonizer AI not appear as an active outfit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Outfit Lua function onshoot has been renamed onshootany&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can toggle point defense weapons on and off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI will turn off weapons ionizer when going for a kill&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Player’s new ships should start will all the default outfits, which fixes the some Sirius psychic tests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pilot.weapsetAdd follows the same logic as the normal equipping functions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;slim GUI uses primary/secondary colours like the info menu&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI should be less prone to jump before their leader&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed cargo being lost when swapping ships in missions and events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;chapter1&lt;/code&gt;: event claims all the systems just in case&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;poi&lt;/code&gt;: renamed ‘Pristine Derelict’ to ‘Unusual Derelict’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;poi_intro&lt;/code&gt;: fixed typo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;achack03&lt;/code&gt;: fixed mission not being acceptable and harja spawning forever&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;achack04&lt;/code&gt;: fixed missing formatting string&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;dv_bikers&lt;/code&gt;: made missiles significantly more dodgeable and changed location&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Translation updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>

