<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="https://naev.org/">
  <id>https://naev.org/</id>
  <title>Naev Blarg</title>
  <updated>2024-12-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <link rel="self" href="https://naev.org/feed/index.xml" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <author>
    <name>Naev DevTeam</name>
    <uri>https://naev.org</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2024-12-23:/blarg/2024-12-23_0.12.0/</id>
    <title type="html">Naev 0.12.0</title>
    <published>2024-12-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-12-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2024-12-23_0.12.0/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a whole month of beta testing and furious bug fixing, following the
tradition, we are once again doing our yearly release. This release includes
many engine improvements, such as 3D ships, an in-game wiki, reworked weapon
sets, notable performance increases, etc., but also a significant amount of new
content including a whole new area, more and reworked missions, and ship
variants among others things. We also have not forgotten significant quality of
life improvements; folding messages, more visual indications for things such as
important characters at the spaceport bar, filtering for the mission computer,
and more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank all the contributors who participated and helped in the
making of this release that we hope will both surprise new players and veterans
alike!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most notable changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nearly all the ships are now modeled in 3D with fancy lighting and tilting effects!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can now capture ships!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New ships and ship variants!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Faction reputation is no longer a single global value, but more nuanced and local.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simplified and more powerful weapon sets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New challenging area to access many secrets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In-game Wiki full of mechanics and lore explanations!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get the latest version from any of the following sources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/v0.12.0"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/github.svg" alt="Get - Github" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/598530/Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/steam.svg" alt="Get - Steam" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://naev.itch.io/naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/itchio.svg" alt="Get - Itch.io" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://flathub.org/apps/details/org.naev.Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/flathub.svg" alt="Get - Flathub" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new version should be compatible with older save games, and will update
things as necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive video720p"&gt;
 &lt;div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 figure-img"&gt;
  &lt;video controls="" class="embed-responsive-item"&gt;
   &lt;source src="/videos/0.11.0_trailer.webm" type="video/webm;codecs=&amp;quot;vp9, opus&amp;quot;" /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Naev 0.11.0 official trailer.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id="full-changelog"&gt;Full Changelog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gameplay
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ability to capture disabled ships&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Faction reputation is no longer universal, but varies on systems
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Direct faction hit changes are shown as messages&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Your actions will more directly affect ships in the system&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Significantly increase maximum potential fleet capacity&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Excess energy to battery recharge efficiency is now flat instead of varying based on charge level&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Gave the Za’lek Sting a slight detection buff &lt;!-- codespell:ignore sting --&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can only have a single patrol mission active at a given time&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pirates are less numerous during Chapter 0&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dvaered Arsenal has no fighter bays and fewer slots&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lowered CPU cost of some fighter bays&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Decreased CPU and energy provided by large core slots&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pillaging ships affects reputation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Significantly increased the amount of fuel provided by outfits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Camouflage burster gives a speed bonus while active and disables when out of stealth&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can scan ships with ‘u’ key&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Gave the Quicksilver another medium structural slot&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Beam weapons have minimum delays instead of minimum durations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can stealth when missiles are locked on&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Deployed fighters take stress and damage over time when their mother ship is destroyed&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Electron Burst Cannons and Za’lek Heavy Drones have had their damage per second lowered&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improved point defense
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Spittle Tubuloid Cluster is now a utility and does more damage&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Guardian Interception System does double damage&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Missiles explode when intercepted&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bounties have explicit time limits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Derelicts should appear in remote systems&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quality of Life
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added colourblind correction mode&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Exposed more colourblind options to the user&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can modify game speed directly instead of using a slow mode difficulty for accessibility&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Messages get folded instead of repeating&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Asteroids no longer fade out if close to or targeted by the player&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Display fuel consumption for ships in the equipment overlay&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added option to match speed with the slowest ship in the fleet (on by default)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Made it so ships in the equipment screen do not change order based on value&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mark spaceport bar tab when there is an important NPC&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Weapon set keybindings change window tabs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use short outfit names when displaying groups of outfits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shown more useful things you have when buying outfits with things other than credits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can sort and filter the mission computer&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added small optional bounce to NPCs when they start talking&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Inform the player when they don’t meet mission requirements for some important missions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can add new plugins directly from the options menu&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can toggle whether autonav stops when missile lock-ons are detected&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added colour coded factional backgrounds in the shipyard&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can rotate shipyard image for ships with 3D graphics&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Prompt when deleting notes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added accessibility option that allows skipping story minigames&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can view and change all your ships in the equipment tab when there is refuelling&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reduced space dust size by 50%&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Changed mouse click selection priority, it prefers spobs/jumps and will ignore clicks reselecting the same object&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Content
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New in-game wiki with explanation on gameplay mechanics and lots of lore&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;8 new missions
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;The Onions call&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4 new ships&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;13 new ship variants
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Give a new twist to existing ships&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;6 new outfits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New area with unique challenges&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New events
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Get more Sirius abilities&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Find the dark side of the Nebula&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New NPC portraits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New generic NPC and News messages&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reworked trails to make ships feel more speedy&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engine
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for 3D models
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Lighting is based on system stars&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Fancy effects for special systems&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Ships tilt slightly when rotating&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Simple animations are supported and used when applicable&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for an in-game wiki
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Can process YAML, Lua, and markdown&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Cross-link support&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Support for custom widgets&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stats (except inverted stats) are now additive instead of multiplicative&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try to merge saves if multiple directories correspond to the same player&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More robust weapon set support that can handle multiple overlapping weapon sets&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Faster handling of asteroids with large exclusion areas&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added fuel_usage_mod ship stat&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed player losing navigation targets when unidiff is applied&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed ai.idir giving wrong answer by M_PI_2 in some cases&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Threaded more loading components&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lua require now caches chunks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dropped SDL_image fallback&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use higher internal timer for all platforms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for Tracy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Spobs that are not landable yet generate presence will be shown on the map&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Warn the player if they try to use a name with all space characters&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Decoupled the collision system from the rendering system&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added a low memory mode to use fewer and smaller textures with 3D&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lazy load ship and outfit graphics to reduce memory usage and decrease load time&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use clang-format to format all the C code&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use enums internally to represent keybindings instead of strings&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Always use replaygain information when available when loading vorbis files&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stop repeating the same warning after a fixed amount of times&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for outfits that don’t break stealth&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Editor has partial support for universe diffs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Editor has separate configuration and file dialogues&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New ship stats
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Global weapon range, damage, fire-rate and energy usage&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Range ship stat for all specific weapon types&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Turn, speed, and accel for launchers&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Shield downtime modifier&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Deprecated old faction API in favour of the new one for local / global standings&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added support for temporarily overriding faction standings&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;PSO and Mizar nebulas have trails again&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Removed fancy background mode&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can remove fighter bays with deployed fighters&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sol is less friendly&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed rare cases where fighters would not be able to dock&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed hypergate and wormhole effects getting stuck&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Obelisks tell if you have completed them already&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed space dust disappearing with certain jump abilities&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Boarded pilots become permanently disabled if they lose space-worthiness&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Double tap will activate feather drive like blink engines&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed camouflage burster not activating stealth&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed bug where beams were counted as giving energy in the equipment optimizer&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;shadowvigil: claim entire route&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;sh01_corvette: should be completable on easy difficulties now&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;patrol: fixed escorts and fighters becoming hostile if hostile to the mission giving faction&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed debugging paranoid builds under Windows&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed autonav not respecting shield thresholds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;zbh10: Godheart and friends get at most 1 fighter bay per ship now&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed ESS Trinity being bribeable&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cargo on fleets with be displayed to make room for mission cargo when necessary&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Made it so Shadow Vigil doesn’t try to go through Surano system for reasons&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;blackhole/zbh09&lt;/code&gt;: fixed softlock during a cutscene under certain conditions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Don’t play wormhole sound on main menu&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Don’t allow the player to sell unique ships&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed corner cases where destroyed player ships would not properly be updated&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed Sirius Providence flow absorption bonus&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed positioning of a certain blockade&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed some visual aberrations when forcing the player to land or jump&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Prioritize pilots and other objects over uninhabited planets when clicking&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can always bribe your way to pirate’s clansworlds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Consistently colour the ShipAI messages in the tutorial&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Made max_fps actually get respected&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed map decorators not shown in editor&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Update the overlay scaling given the player’s position&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed population not being updated by universe diffs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed date acquired being wrong on some platforms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improved pilot facing corrections when jumping&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pirate ambush derelict events break stealth&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mining minigame result affects yield more&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Absorption is no longer limited to the 0% to 100% range&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;derelict_rescue: only allow generic target space objects&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Restored portable installs with the Windows installer&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Show intrinsic outfits in the “Other” tab&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed plural form of 0 items in many cases&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ships significantly past the mass limit are no longer space worthy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Don’t allow ship shield/energy to go negative&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Jumping through a one-way normal / hidden jump reveals the hidden side&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Increased nebula visibility by 400 km&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed map thresholds for interference&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Editor now shows dialogues on errors and allows user to choose directory to save data to&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Escorts will try to respect player’s autonav rules by default&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Don’t show stealth circles during cinematics&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Made pilots in formation less prone to spinning&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Workaround MESA driver bug that causes dark or invisible ships on AMD hardware&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can no longer abort missions during landing animation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2024-12-11:/blarg/2024-12-11_0.12.0-beta.3/</id>
    <title type="html">Naev 0.12.0-beta.3</title>
    <published>2024-12-11T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-12-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2024-12-11_0.12.0-beta.3/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With the bug frenzy calming down, we are proud to announce version 0.12.0-beta.3.
This release contains a myriad of bug fixes and should be quite close to the final 0.12.0 version that is planned before the end of the year.
As always, please report any issues on &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/issues"&gt;this tracker&lt;/a&gt;,
and feel free to join our Discord or Matrix chatrooms. Find out more about them &lt;a href="https://naev.org/contact/"&gt;here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get the new version from any of the sources below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/v0.12.0-beta.3"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/github.svg" alt="Get - Github" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/598530/Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/steam.svg" alt="Get - Steam" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://naev.itch.io/naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/itchio.svg" alt="Get - Itch.io" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://flathub.org/apps/details/org.naev.Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/flathub.svg" alt="Get - Flathub" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="As a new ship variant of the Llama, the Llama Voyager shares many features but has fundamental differences such as fuel regeneration." src="/imgs/screenshots_0.12.0/llama_voyager.png" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;As a new ship variant of the Llama, the Llama Voyager shares many features but has fundamental differences such as fuel regeneration.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changes-since-0120-beta2"&gt;Changes since 0.12.0-beta.2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed collisions for some ships at certain angles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changed mouse click selection priority, it prefers spobs/jumps and will ignore clicks reselecting the same object&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed map decorators not shown in editor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Centered buttons at the top of the holo-archives&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Show if a system has a bar in the map&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed conf.mouse_doubleclick not disabling when set to 0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed crashes when a faction is assigned a non-existent colour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update the overlay scaling given the player’s position&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed population not being updated by universe diffs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed date acquired being wrong on some platforms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Round reputation values when displaying standing text for consistency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Display local standing in the information window&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed certain combination of opening menus locking up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed fmt.number displaying wrong values when negative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed spoiling of system names on the map&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improved pilot facing corrections when jumping&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can no longer abort missions during landing animation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed editor crash with empty descriptions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed editor crash when making links to systems with no presence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed rehabilitation missions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed escorts not using special outfits and abilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed escort fighters existing after undeploying escort&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed Certitude trails&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pirate ambush derelict events break stealth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mining minigame result affects yield more&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Absorption is no longer limited to the 0% to 100% range&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;derelict_rescue: only allow generic target space objects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;onion04: don’t fail if something happens to the gawain after taking the cargo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;traffic_01: don’t use hardcoded systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bounty: fixed error with deadlines in certain cases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;neburesearch04: don’t let the drones see through stealth and disable the player from relanding to skip stage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;minerva/judugement: fixed error in VN flow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minor typo fixes and translation updates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased maxmimum reputation for a certain hidden faction to 70&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restored portable installs with the Windows installer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Documentation fixes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minor typo fixes and translation updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2024-11-28:/blarg/2024-11-28_0.12.0-beta.2/</id>
    <title type="html">Naev 0.12.0-beta.2</title>
    <published>2024-11-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-11-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2024-11-28_0.12.0-beta.2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A lot of major and minor issues, in addition to some minor new features, have
been resolved calling for a 0.12.0-beta.2. In particular, support for lowering
the saturation of the nebula, and having escorts respect your autonav
preferences (you can disable it in the settings from the info menu) have been
added as new features. We don’t have any intention of adding any new features
before the final 0.12.0 version, and will keep on resolving bugs as they are
found.
As always, please report any issues on &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/issues"&gt;this tracker&lt;/a&gt;,
and feel free to join our Discord or Matrix chatrooms. Find out more about them &lt;a href="https://naev.org/contact/"&gt;here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get the new version from any of the sources below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/v0.12.0-beta.2"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/github.svg" alt="Get - Github" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/598530/Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/steam.svg" alt="Get - Steam" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://naev.itch.io/naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/itchio.svg" alt="Get - Itch.io" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://flathub.org/apps/details/org.naev.Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/flathub.svg" alt="Get - Flathub" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="As a new ship variant of the Llama, the Llama Voyager shares many features but has fundamental differences such as fuel regeneration." src="/imgs/screenshots_0.12.0/llama_voyager.png" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;As a new ship variant of the Llama, the Llama Voyager shares many features but has fundamental differences such as fuel regeneration.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id="changes-since-0120-beta1"&gt;Changes since 0.12.0-beta.1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fallback for missing holo archives ship entries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reset proteron reputation more aggressively&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed overlap in VN logs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Show intrinsic outfits in the “Other” tab&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shooting weapons no longer resets autonav speed up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed plural form of 0 items in many cases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Made pilots in formation less prone to spinning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ships significantly past the mass limit are no longer space worthy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lowered the price of a certain map&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lowered presence of a certain faction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prevent changing autonav target via Lua when jumping&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Disable jettisoning cargo when landing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Removed overlap in the options menu&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t allow ship shield/energy to go negative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t show stealth circles during cinematics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jumping through a one-way normal / hidden jump reveals the hidden side&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Escorts will try to respect player’s autonav rules by default&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased nebula visibility by 400 km&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed text overlap in the holo-archives for certain languages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed reputation changes not working on dynamic factions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed text overlap if ship name is too long&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed automatic weapon sets behaving oddly with multiple ships&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed rare crash when setting hook on non-existent pilot&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed map thresholds for interference&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed some reputation values not being correctly rounded&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed OSD not advancing in a certain mission&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed Sirius Divinity collisions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed beam weapons in “in range” mode not respecting range bonus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed hiding mission OSDs and changing priority being reset on take off or jump&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed asking your ship AI for advice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed point defense requiring toggling thrice to turn off in some cases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sensor anomaly: Nelly will no longer appear in too dangerous or risky systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mephisto type v: lowered heat generation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;seek_n_destroy: fixed hints breaking in certain cases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pir_hit_intro: fixed OSD being displayed wrong&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taiomi04: update OSD after boarding ship&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bounty: fixed OSD getting reset after killing/capturing target&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ant_supplies: fixed hostility after jumping into system again&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Editor now shows dialogues on errors and allows user to choose directory to save data to&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minor typo fixes and translation updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2024-11-16:/blarg/2024-11-16_0.12.0-beta.1/</id>
    <title type="html">Naev 0.12.0-beta.1</title>
    <published>2024-11-16T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-11-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2024-11-16_0.12.0-beta.1/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This year, we’re starting the betas a bit early given the large amount of
content modified and added. As always, this release contains a large amount of
changes done during the past year which likely have introduced a lot of bugs
and issues that we want to iron out before the final release of 0.12.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this release changes a lot of how the game currently plays, and, while it
is highly recommended to start a new game, it should be possible to just load
up your old saves without too much stuff being changed. In particular, some of
the major changes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nearly all the ships are now modeled in 3D with fancy lighting and tilting effects!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can now capture ships!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New ships and ship variants!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Faction reputation is no longer a single global value, but more nuanced and local.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New challenging area to access many secrets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In-game Wiki full of mechanics and lore explanations!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you try it and find any issues, please report them at &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/issues"&gt;the issue
tracker&lt;/a&gt;. Discussion about the game can be
had on one of the various discussion forums and chatrooms we have. Check them
out &lt;a href="https://naev.org/contact/"&gt;here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get the new version from any of the sources below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/v0.12.0-beta.1"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/github.svg" alt="Get - Github" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/598530/Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/steam.svg" alt="Get - Steam" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://naev.itch.io/naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/itchio.svg" alt="Get - Itch.io" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://flathub.org/apps/details/org.naev.Naev"&gt;&lt;img src="/imgs/badges/flathub.svg" alt="Get - Flathub" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="As a new ship variant of the Llama, the Llama Voyager shares many features but has fundamental differences such as fuel regeneration." src="/imgs/screenshots_0.12.0/llama_voyager.png" width="720" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;As a new ship variant of the Llama, the Llama Voyager shares many features but has fundamental differences such as fuel regeneration.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id="full-changelog"&gt;Full Changelog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gameplay
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ability to capture disabled ships&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Faction reputation is no longer universal, but varies on systems
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Direct faction hit changes are shown as messages&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Your actions will more directly affect ships in the system&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Significantly increase maximum potential fleet capacity&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Excess energy to battery recharge efficiency is now a flat 50% instead of varying based on charge level&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Gave the Za’lek sting a slight detection buff &lt;!-- codespell:ignore sting --&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can only have a single patrol mission active at a given time&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pirates are less numerous during Chapter 0&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dvaered Arsenal has no fighter bays and fewer slots&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lowered CPU cost of some fighter bays&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Decreased CPU and energy provided by large core slots&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pillaging ships affects reputation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Significantly increased the amount of fuel provided by outfits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Camouflage burster gives a speed bonus while active and disables when out of stealth&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can scan ships with ‘u’ key&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Gave the Quicksilver another medium structural slot&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Beam weapons have minimum delays instead of minimum durations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can stealth when missiles are locked on&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Deployed fighters take stress and damage over time when their mother ship is destroyed&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Electron Burst Cannons and Za’lek Heavy Drones have had their damage per second lowered&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improved point defense
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Spittle Tubuloid Cluster is now a utility and does more damage&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Guardian Interception System does double damage&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Missiles explode when intercepted&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bounties have explicit time limits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Derelicts should appear in remote systems&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quality of Life
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added colourblind correction mode&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Exposed more colourblind options to the user&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can modify game speed directly instead of using a slow mode difficulty for accessibility&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Messages get folded instead of repeating&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Asteroids no longer fade out if close to or targeted by the player&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Display fuel consumption for ships in the equipment overlay&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added option to match speed with the slowest ship in the fleet (on by default)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Made it so ships in the equipment screen do not change order based on value&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mark spaceport bar tab when there is an important NPC&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Weapon set keybindings change window tabs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use short outfit names when displaying groups of outfits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shown more useful things you have when buying outfits with things other than credits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can sort and filter the mission computer&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added small optional bounce to NPCs when they start talking&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Inform the player when they don’t meet mission requirements for some important missions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can add new plugins directly from the options menu&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can toggle whether autonav stops when missile lock-ons are detected&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added colour coded factional backgrounds in the shipyard&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can rotate shipyard image for ships with 3D graphics&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Prompt when deleting notes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added accessibility option that allows skipping story minigames&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can view and change all your ships in the equipment tab when there is refuelling&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reduced space dust size by 50%&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Content
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New in-game wiki with explanation on gameplay mechanics and lots of lore&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;8 new missions
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;The Onions call&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4 new ships&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;13 new ship variants
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Give a new twist to existing ships&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;6 new outfits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New area with unique challenges&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New events
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Get more Sirius abilities&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Find the dark side of the Nebula&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New NPC portraits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New generic NPC and News messages&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reworked trails to make ships feel more speedy&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engine
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for 3D models
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Lighting is based on system stars&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Fancy effects for special systems&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Ships tilt slightly when rotating&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Simple animations are supported and used when applicable&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for an in-game wiki
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Can process YAML, Lua, and markdown&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Cross-link support&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Support for custom widgets&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stats (except inverted stats) are now additive instead of multiplicative&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try to merge saves if multiple directories correspond to the same player&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More robust weapon set support that can handle multiple overlapping weapon sets&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Faster handling of asteroids with large exclusion areas&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added fuel_usage_mod ship stat&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed player losing navigation targets when unidiff is applied&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed ai.idir giving wrong answer by M_PI_2 in some cases&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Threaded more loading components&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lua require now caches chunks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dropped SDL_image fallback&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use higher internal timer for all platforms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for Tracy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Spobs that are not landable yet generate presence will be shown on the map&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Warn the player if they try to use a name with all space characters&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Decoupled the collision system from the rendering system&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added a low memory mode to use fewer and smaller textures with 3D&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lazy load ship and outfit graphics to reduce memory usage and decrease load time&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use clang-format to format all the C code&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use enums internally to represent keybindings instead of strings&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Always use replaygain information when available when loading vorbis files&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stop repeating the same warning after a fixed amount of times&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Support for outfits that don’t break stealth&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Editor has partial support for universe diffs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Editor has separate configuration and file dialogues&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New ship stats
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Global weapon range, damage, fire-rate and energy usage&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Range ship stat for all specific weapon types&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Turn, speed, and accel for launchers&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Shield downtime modifier&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Deprecated old faction API in favour of the new one for local / global standings&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Added support for temporarily overriding faction standings&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;PSO and Mizar nebulas have trails again&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Removed fancy background mode&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can remove fighter bays with deployed fighters&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sol is less friendly&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed rare cases where fighters would not be able to dock&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed hypergate and wormhole effects getting stuck&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Obelisks tell if you have completed them already&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed space dust disappearing with certain jump abilities&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Boarded pilots become permanently disabled if they lose space-worthiness&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Double tap will activate feather drive like blink engines&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed camouflage burster not activating stealth&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed bug where beams were counted as giving energy in the equipment optimizer&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;shadowvigil: claim entire route&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;sh01_corvette: should be completable on easy difficulties now&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;patrol: fixed escorts and fighters becoming hostile if hostile to the mission giving faction&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed debugging paranoid builds under Windows&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed autonav not respecting shield thresholds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;zbh10: Godheart and friends get at most 1 fighter bay per ship now&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixed ESS Trinity being bribeable&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cargo on fleets with be displayed to make room for mission cargo when necessary&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Made it so Shadow Vigil doesn’t try to go through Surano system for reasons&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;blackhole/zbh09&lt;/code&gt;: fixed softlock during a cutscene under certain conditions&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:naev.org,2024-07-21:/blarg/2024-07-21_sporadic_naev_newsletter_vol_4/</id>
    <title type="html">Sporadic Naev Newsletter Vol. 4</title>
    <published>2024-07-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-07-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://naev.org/blarg/2024-07-21_sporadic_naev_newsletter_vol_4/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This year we’re having another edition of our Sporadic Naev Newsletter. We’ll be covering &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/blob/main/CHANGELOG"&gt;some of the improvements&lt;/a&gt; that will appear in the 0.12.0 release, and more importantly, discuss a feature almost 15 years in the making: Naev going 3D! Now, this doesn’t mean gameplay is going 3D - gameplay is fundamentally unchanged - however, the ship models are now in 3D, allowing us to do new fancy effects and lower memory consumption while at it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive video720p"&gt;
 &lt;div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 figure-img"&gt;
  &lt;video controls="" class="embed-responsive-item"&gt;
   &lt;source src="/videos/blarg/2024/3dspin.webm" type="video/webm;codecs=&amp;quot;vp9, opus&amp;quot;" /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Nearly all ships are now in 3D!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id="less-pirates-in-the-early-game"&gt;Less Pirates in the Early Game&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the major complaints that Naev always gets is how ruthless pirates are, especially in the early game, when the player has no proper defenses. Although the past several releases have tried to mitigate the issue by establishing a safe starting area with no pirates, and adding more introductory missions to help the player get started, for those players that strayed too far from the starting area, it was often fatal. Now, Chapter 0 will feature significantly less pirates, that will ramp up to normal when the player reaches Chapter 1. This should give the player time to get better ships and survive the pirate menace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="Universe diff support in the universe editor." src="/imgs/blarg/2024/uniedit_diff.png" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Universe diff support in the universe editor.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to implement this feature, the in-game universe editor was significantly reworked (yet again!) to support universe diffs, that is, instead of saving the entire universe, only changes with the default are saved. While this has been used only for reducing pirates, for now, this is going to come very in hand when implementing the next stages of the major campaigns, where the universe will undergo many significant changes. It will definitely be a good investment for things to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="naev-now-in-3d"&gt;Naev, now in 3D!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while this is something that was proposed around 15 years ago, this is something that has been quite active in the works for almost 5 years now. During that time, it has been rewritten twice: first using object files and more traditional rendering, and now using gltf files with physically-based rendering. As we’re not using any sort of game engine, it was all written from the ground up, and includes some fancy things like variance shadow maps, FidelityFX filtering, high dynamic tone mapping, and super sampling. There’s still many things to do, but this finally lets us start to do fancier things that were infeasible using spritesheets. That said, spritesheets are still supported, however, 3D models are the recommended way of adding new ships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="The system you are in will subtly change the lighting on all ships." src="/imgs/blarg/2024/3dlighting.png" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;The system you are in will subtly change the lighting on all ships.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has taken a lot of work, but all the ancient models have been updated to work with the newest blender, and many models have seen upgrades in different aspects like texturing, engine glows, broken geometry, and animations. Some ships have had to be nearly completely remade to work with current standards. There’s still a lot to do, but they look much better, and the same model can be used in the shipyard, communication window, and in-game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive video720p"&gt;
 &lt;div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 figure-img"&gt;
  &lt;video controls="" class="embed-responsive-item"&gt;
   &lt;source src="/videos/blarg/2024/3dzebra.webm" type="video/webm;codecs=&amp;quot;vp9, opus&amp;quot;" /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;3D models support animations, such as the Zebra having rotating parts.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 3D, we finally can also have ships tilt slightly when turning. This makes flying feel much more natural, and the tilt shows off more highlights and details of the ships. While we were hoping to add blinking lights and more details, those have not yet been implemented, but there is a real possibility that they will come sooner and later, once some logistics are figured out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive video720p"&gt;
 &lt;div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 figure-img"&gt;
  &lt;video controls="" class="embed-responsive-item"&gt;
   &lt;source src="/videos/blarg/2024/3dgoddard.webm" type="video/webm;codecs=&amp;quot;vp9, opus&amp;quot;" /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;Ships tilt slightly when turning. Weapon mounts and trails adjust to the 3D models.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, only ships have been reworked into 3D, but we hope to have planets, stations, and asteroids to join them in the near future. Some effects such as the backgrounds, wormholes, and the likes will still be kept in 2D, however, it will all work much better together. Oh, and last but not least, we’ve taken this opportunity to add 4 new ships to flesh out a bit more the Naev universe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="linear-energy-regeneration"&gt;Linear Energy Regeneration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although many players had not noticed, energy regeneration in Naev used an RC (Resistance-Capacitor) charge curve, which meant that energy would regenerate faster the less you had, and slowly taper out. This was not properly conveyed to the player and has now made linear. Now 100 GW of energy regeneration will always be 100 GJ of energy generated per second. While it is not possible to keep exactly the same behaviour as before, outfits and ships have been adjusted to try to be as similar as before the change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="quality-of-life-for-all"&gt;Quality of Life for all!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of Quality of Life has also made it into the nightly. Spaceport bar is marked with red exclamation points when there is an interesting NPC, there is support for sorting and filtering mission computer missions, repeated messages get folded in the GUI, asteroids won’t disappear when the player is nearby or actively targeting them, and much more! This should ensure a smoother experience for the players and get rid of lots of small friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="figure embed-responsive" style="text-align:center;"&gt;
  &lt;div class="embed-responsive figure-img"&gt;
    &lt;img class="img-fluid" alt="You can now sort missions and it is easier to tell when new missions are available at the spaceport bar." src="/imgs/blarg/2024/qol.png" /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption"&gt;You can now sort missions and it is easier to tell when new missions are available at the spaceport bar.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the game uses lazy loading and threading to load much faster than before, starting up much faster and using less memory in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="concluding-remarks"&gt;Concluding Remarks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the aforementioned fixes can be already tasted in the nightly branch which can be obtained through the steam beta, &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/releases/tag/nightly"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://naev.itch.io/naev"&gt;itch.io&lt;/a&gt;. They will be included in the next 0.12.0 release which is scheduled for December if you’d rather wait for a more stable release instead of risking the bleeding edge. If you’re interested in seeing the full changelog, including things that have not been discussed here, it’s &lt;a href="https://github.com/naev/naev/blob/main/CHANGELOG"&gt;available on github&lt;/a&gt;.
With that, this concludes the Sporadic Naev Newsletter Vol. 4, and see you again in the next one!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>

